[
    {
        "question": "1. Newly formed DNA copies may not be identical at times. Give one reason. (NCERT, AI 2017)",
        "answer": "1. When a cell reproduces, DNA replication occurs which results in formation of two similar copies of DNA. The process of copying the DNA leads to some variations each time. As a result, the DNA copies produced are similar to each other but sometimes may not identical."
    },
    {
        "question": "2. When a cell reproduces, what happens to its DNA? (AI 2017)",
        "answer": "2. When a cell reproduces, DNA replication occurs which forms two similar copies of DNA."
    },
    {
        "question": "3. What is DNA? (Delhi 2016, Foreign 2015)",
        "answer": "3. DNA (deoxyribonucleic acid) is a polymer made up of large number of nucleotide units. It carries genetic information from generation to generation."
    },
    {
        "question": "4. Name the life process of an organism that helps in the growth of its population. (AI 2015)  SA II (3 marks)",
        "answer": "4. Reproduction is a life process that helps in multiplication of an organism and growth of its population."
    },
    {
        "question": "5. Reproduction is one of the most important characteristic of living beings. Give three reasons in support of the statement. (AI 2017)",
        "answer": "5. Reproduction is one of the most important characteristics of living beings because: (i) it is essential for existence and continuity of a species. (ii) it helps to pass genetic information to next generation. (iii) it brings variations in next generation which is the basis for evolution."
    },
    {
        "question": "6. Define reproduction. How does it helps in providing stability to the population of species?(NCERT Exemplar, Al 2016)",
        "answer": "6. The production of new organisms by the existing organisms of the same species is known as reproduction. It is linked to the stability of population of a species. DNA replication during reproduction ensures transfer of specific characters or body design features that is essential for an individual of a population to live and use that particular niche. Some variations present in a few individuals of population caused due to reproduction which also helps in their survival at changing niches."
    },
    {
        "question": "7. What is DNA copying? State its importance. (NCERT Intext, Delhi 2015)",
        "answer": "7. DNA copying is the production of similar copies of DNA present in a cell using various chemical reactions. DNA copying is essential for reproduction through which the organisms pass on their body features to their offspring. Moreover, minor alternations during the process of DNA copying result in the production of variations. Such variations are useful for the survival of species over time."
    },
    {
        "question": "8. What is the effect of DNA copying, which is not perfectly accurate, on the reproduction process? How does the amount of DNA remain constant through each new generation is a combination of DNA copies of two individuals? (AI 2014) LA (5 marks) (a) What is reproduction? List its two types. (b) How are the modes of reproduction different in unicellular and multicellular organisms? (2019)",
        "answer": "8. In the process of reproduction, if DNA copying is not perfectly accurate, variation occurs. These in turn may allow few individuals of a population to survive in an altered niche and becomes the basis of evolution and over time. Such variations are useful for the survival of species. The combination of DNA copies of two individuals (male and female) occurs during sexual reproduction. Reduction division (meiosis) during gamete formation halves the chromosome number in both male and female gametes. Since these two gametes fuse during fertilisation, the original number of chromosomes (as in the parent) is restored in the offspring. By this way the amount of DNA remains constant in each new generation. Concept Applied Reduction division occurs during sexual reproduction."
    },
    {
        "question": "10. Assertion (A): Amoeba always produces two daughter amoebae while Plasmodium divides into many daughter cells. Reason (R): Amoeba undergoes binary fission while Plasmodium undergoes multiple fission. (a) Both (A) and (R) are true and (R) is the correct explanation of the assertion (A). (b) Both (A) and (R) are true, but (R) is not the correct explanation of the assertion (A). (c) (A) is true, but (R) is false. (d) (A) is false, but (R) is true. (2020 C) VSA (1 mark)",
        "answer": "10. (a) Amoeba reproduce through binary fission and produces two daughter amoebae. Plasmodium reproduces through multiple fission and splits to form many new organisms."
    },
    {
        "question": "11. Define fragmentation. (2021 C)",
        "answer": "11. Fragmentation is the mode of reproduction in which parent body breaks into two or more fragments and each fragment develops into a new individual. E.g., Spirogyra."
    },
    {
        "question": "12. Name the method by which Spirogyra reproduces under favourable conditions. Is this method sexual or asexual? (Delhi 2017)",
        "answer": "12. The method by which Spirogyra reproduces under favorable conditions is fragmentation. This is an asexual mode of reproduction."
    },
    {
        "question": "13. How does Plasmodium reproduce? Is this method sexual or asexual? (Delhi 2017)",
        "answer": "13. Plasmodium reproduces through multiple fission method. In this method, the parent organism splits to form many new organisms at the same time. This is an asexual method of reproduction."
    },
    {
        "question": "14. Name the part of Bryophyllum where the buds are produced for vegetative propagation. (Delhi 2016)",
        "answer": "14. Bryophyllum propagates vegetatively by the buds produced at the margins of leaves."
    },
    {
        "question": "15. What happens when a mature Spirogyra filament attains considerable length? (AI 2016)",
        "answer": "15. When a mature Spirogyra filament attains considerable length it simply breaks into two or more fragments and each fragment, then grows into a new Spirogyra."
    },
    {
        "question": "16. Name the method by which Hydra reproduces. Is this method sexual or asexual? (Foreign 2016)",
        "answer": "16. Hydra generally reproduces through budding. It is an asexual method of reproduction."
    },
    {
        "question": "17. Name two simple organisms having the ability of regeneration. (AI 2015)",
        "answer": "17. Hydra and Planaria are two organisms that have the ability to regenerate."
    },
    {
        "question": "18. Name the causative agent of the disease \"Kala-azar\" and its mode of asexual reproduction. (Foreign 2015) SAI (2 marks)",
        "answer": "18. Causative agent of the disease Kala-azar is Leishmania. It reproduces asexually by binary fission."
    },
    {
        "question": "19. (a) Name the reproductive and non-reproductive (b) List any two advantages of vegetative propagation. (Term II, 2021-22, Foreign 2015)",
        "answer": "19. (a) Reproductive part of bread mould or Rhizopus- Sporangia, a bob like structure which contain spores. Non-reproductive part - Hyphae, which are thread like structures developed on bread. (b) Advantages of vegetative propagation: (i) It produces a large number of plants in shortest time. (ii) All plants produced are genetically similar to parent, preserves purity, resistance and good qualities."
    },
    {
        "question": "20. (a) Name the process shown below and define it: (b) Name the type of cells present in the organisms which exhibit this process. (Term II, 2021-22) Ev",
        "answer": "20. (a) The process shown is regeneration in Planaria. Regeneration is the ability to give rise to a new individual from any broken or injured body part. (b) Regeneration in Planaria is carried out by specialised cells known as neoblasts (stem cells)."
    },
    {
        "question": "21. After examining a prepared slide under the high power of a compound microscope, a student concludes that the given slide shows the various stages of binary fission in a unicellular organism. Write two observations on the basis of which such a conclusion may be drawn. (2019)",
        "answer": "21. The two observations that was taken by the student that concludes that the given slide shows the various stages of binary fission in a unicellular organism are as follows: (i) Presence of unicellular and uninucleate organism showing irregular outline. (ii) Division of nucleus of parent cell into two equal halves."
    },
    {
        "question": "22. Define multiple fission. Give its one example. (2019, Foreign 2014)",
        "answer": "22. Multiple fission is an asexual mode of reproduction in which the parent organism splits to form many new organisms at the same time. Multiple fission occurs in Plasmodium."
    },
    {
        "question": "23. Write two differences between binary fission and multiple fission in a tabular form. (NCERT Intext, Delhi 2015)",
        "answer": "23. Differences between binary fission and multiple fission are as follows:"
    },
    {
        "question": "24. List four modes of asexual reproduction other than fission in the living organisms. (Delhi 2014)",
        "answer": "24. The four modes of asexual reproduction other than fission in living organisms are : (i) budding (iii) regeneration and (ii) spore formation (iv) fragmentation."
    },
    {
        "question": "25. List four advantages of vegetative propagation. (Delhi 2014)",
        "answer": "25. Four advantages of vegetative propagation are as follows: (i) The characters of the parent plants are preserved hence a good variety produced can be propagated by vegetative means. (ii) The plants, which do not produce viable seeds or produce very few seeds, can be reproduced by this method. For example, banana, potato, grapes, sugarcane, rose, orange, etc. (iii) It is an easier, quicker and cheaper method of propagation. (iv) It is easier to get rid of pathogen from any part of plant by vegetative propagation."
    },
    {
        "question": "26. Draw labelled diagrams to illustrate budding in Hydra. (AI 2014)",
        "answer": "26. The given diagram illustrates budding in Hydra:"
    },
    {
        "question": "27. How do Plasmodium and Leishmania reproduce? Write one difference in their mode of reproduction. (Foreign 2014) SA II (3 marks)",
        "answer": "27. Plasmodium and Leishmania reproduce by the process of fission which is an asexual mode of reproduction. Plasmodium reproduces by multiple fission. About 1000 daughter cells are produced by the multiple fission of a Plasmodium. Leishmania reproduces by the process of binary fission. In Leishmania, the splitting of parent cell takes place in a definite plane (longitudinally) with respect to flagellum at its end to produce two daughter cells."
    },
    {
        "question": "28. What is vegetative propagation? List with brief explanation three advantages of practising this process for growing some types of plants. Select two plants from the following which are grown by this process: Banana, Wheat, Mustard, Jasmine, Gram (2020, Foreign 2016)",
        "answer": "28. Vegetative propagation is an asexual method of reproduction in plants. In this method, new plants are obtained from the parts of old plants (like stems, roots and leaves), without the help of any reproductive organs. Advantages of vegetative propagation are as follows: (i) Vegetative propagation is usually used for the propagation of those plants which produce either very few seeds or do not produce viable seeds. (ii) Seedless plants can be obtained by artificial vegetative propagation. (iii) Grafting is a propagation method which is very useful for fruit trees and flowering bushes. It enables to combine the most desirable characteristics of two plants. Banana and jasmine are generally grown through vegetative propagation method."
    },
    {
        "question": "29. What happens when (a) accidently, Planaria gets cut into many pieces (b) Bryophyllum leaf falls on the wet soil (c) on maturation sporangia of Rhizopus bursts? (NCERT Exemplar, Delhi 2017)",
        "answer": "29. (a) When Planaria accidently gets cut into many pieces then its each piece grows into a complete organism. This is known as regeneration. (b) When the Bryophyllum leaf falls on the wet soil, the buds present in the notches along the leaf margin develop into new plants. This is known as vegetative propagation. (c) The sporangia of Rhizopus contain cells or spores that can eventually develop into new Rhizopus individuals when it bursts on maturation."
    },
    {
        "question": "30. Describe reproduction by spores in Rhizopus. (AI 2017)",
        "answer": "30. Fungus Rhizopus reproduces by spore formation. During the growth of Rhizopus, small rounded, bulb-like structures develop at the top of the erect hyphae. Such structures are called sporangia. Inside each sporangium, nucleus divides several times. Each nucleus gets surrounded by a little amount of cytoplasm to become spore. Large number of spores are formed inside each sporangium. After sometime sporangium bursts and spores are released in the air. When these spores land on food or soil, under favourable conditions, they germinate into new individuals."
    },
    {
        "question": "31. What is vegetative propagation? State two advantages and two disadvantages of this method. (AI 2017)",
        "answer": "31. Vegetative propagation is a type of asexual reproduction in which the plant parts other than seeds are used as a propagule. Advantages of vegetative propagation: (i) Desirable character of the plant can be preserved through generation. (ii) Seedless plants can be grown via this method. Disadvantages of vegetative propagation: (i) Plants produced by this method posses less vigour and are more prone to diseases. (ii) Plants produced by this method show no genetic variation."
    },
    {
        "question": "32. What is multiple fission? How does it occur in an organism? Explain briefly. Name one organism which exhibits this type of reproduction. (Delhi 2016)",
        "answer": "32. Multiple fission refers to the process of asexual reproduction in which many individuals are formed from a single parent. This method of reproduction occurs in unfavourable conditions. The unicellular organism develops a protective covering called cyst, over the cell. The nucleus of the cell divides repeatedly producing many nuclei. Later on, each nucleus is surrounded by small amount of cytoplasm and many daughter cells are produced within the cyst. When conditions are favourable, the cyst breaks and small offspring are liberated. This type of reproduction is seen in some protozoans, e.g., malarial parasite (Plasmodium)."
    },
    {
        "question": "33. Explain the term \"regeneration” as used in relation to reproduction of organisms. Describe briefly how regeneration is carried out in multicellular organisms like Hydra. (AI 2016)",
        "answer": "33. The process of formation of entire organism from the body parts of a fully differentiated organism is called regeneration. It occurs by process of growth and development. Simple animal like Hydra shows regeneration. When a small piece of Hydra breaks off it grows into complete new Hydra. During regeneration, the cells of cut body part of the organism divide rapidly to make a mass of cells. The cells here move to their proper places within the mass where they have to form different types of tissues. In this way complete organism is regenerated."
    },
    {
        "question": "34. In the context of reproduction of species state the main difference between fission and fragmentation. Also give one example of each.",
        "answer": "34. The main differences between fission and fragmentation are as follows:"
    },
    {
        "question": "35. What happens when (a) Planaria gets cut into two pieces (AI 2016) Ev (b) a mature Spirogyra filament attains considerable length (c) on maturation sporangia burst? (Foreign 2016, Delhi 2016)",
        "answer": "35. (a) When Planaria is cut into two pieces then each piece grows into a complete organism. This is known as regeneration. (b) When a mature Spirogyra filament attains a considerable length it breaks into small pieces called fragments. These fragments grow into new individuals and this mode of reproduction is called fragmentation. (c) When a sporangium burst, large number of spores are released in the air. When these spores land on food or soil, under favourable conditions they germinate into new individuals."
    },
    {
        "question": "36. Explain budding in Hydra with the help of labelled diagrams only.",
        "answer": "36. The given diagram illustrates budding in Hydra:"
    },
    {
        "question": "37. (a) Name the following: (Delhi 2015) (i) Thread like non-reproductive structures present in Rhizopus. (ii) 'Blobs' that develop at the tips of the non- reproductive threads in Rhizopus. (b) Explain how these structures protect themselves and what is the function of the structures released from the 'blobs' in Rhizopus. (Delhi 2015)",
        "answer": "37. (a) (i) Thread like non-reproductive structures present in Rhizopus are called hyphae. (ii) 'Blobs' developing at the tip of hyphae are called sporangia which contain spores. (b) The structures called spores (released from 'blobs') are present in sporangia which can develop into new Rhizopus individuals. These spores are covered with thick walls that protect them until they come in contact with another moist surface and can begin to grow."
    },
    {
        "question": "38. Explain the process of regeneration in Planaria. How is this process different from reproduction? (Foreign 2015, Al 2014)",
        "answer": "38. Regeneration is the formation of the whole body of an organism from its own small fragments. Planaria possesses great power of regeneration. If the body of Planaria somehow gets cut into a number of pieces, then each body piece can regenerate into a complete Planaria by growing all the missing parts. This is shown in given figure: During the process of reproduction, new organism is formed from the complete parent organism. However, during fragmentation, a fragment of original parent body grows into new individual."
    },
    {
        "question": "39. On cutting the body of an organism into many pieces, it was observed that many of these pieces developed as new individuals. Name the process and list two organisms in which this process may be observed. Draw a schematic diagram to illustrate the changes that are likely to be observed during the development of new individuals in any one of the organisms named. (Delhi 2014)",
        "answer": "39. On cutting the body of an organism into many pieces, each of these pieces develop as new individuals. Hydra and Planaria are the organisms in which this process may be observed. Following is the diagram showing development of new individuals by regeneration of body parts of a parent Hydra:"
    },
    {
        "question": "40. Draw diagrams to explain the regeneration that takes place in each of the body parts of Planaria when its body is cut into three pieces. Name any other organism in which a similar process can be observed. (Delhi 2014)",
        "answer": "40. The diagram showing development of new individuals from fragments of Planaria is as follows: Hydra is another organism in which regeneration is observed."
    },
    {
        "question": "41. List any two modes of asexual reproduction in animals. Under which mode of reproduction is vegetative propagation placed and why? List two advantages of vegetative propagation. (AI 2014)",
        "answer": "41. The two modes of asexual reproduction in animals are: (i) fission and (ii) fragmentation. Vegetative propagation is placed under asexual mode of reproduction because in this mode new plants are obtained from the parts of old plants (like stems, roots and leaves), without the help of any reproductive organs. Advantages of vegetative propagation: (i) It produces a large number of plants in shortest time. (ii) All plants produced are genetically similar to parent, preserves purity, resistance and good qualities."
    },
    {
        "question": "42. What is vegetative propagation? List its two advantages. Select two plants raised by this method from the list given below: Wheat, Tomato, Rose, Pea, Gram, Corn, Banana (Foreign 2014)  LA (4/5 marks)",
        "answer": "42. Vegetative propagation is a type of asexual reproduction in which the plant parts other than seeds are used as a propagule. Advantages of vegetative propagation: (i) Desirable character of the plant can be preserved through generation. (ii) Seedless plants can be grown through this method. Banana and rose are propagated by vegetative propagation."
    },
    {
        "question": "43. (i) Name and explain the two modes of asexual reproduction observed in Hydra. (ii) What is vegetative propagation? List two advantages of using this technique. (2023)",
        "answer": "43. (i) Hydra reproduces by two different asexual methods; namely regeneration and budding. Regeneration in Hydra: When a small piece of Hydra breaks off, it grows into complete new Hydra. During regeneration, the cells of cut body part of the organism divide rapidly to make a mass of cells. The cells here move to their proper places within the mass where they have to form different type of tissues. In this way complete organism is regenerated. Given figure shows development of new individuals by regeneration of body parts of a parent Hydra. Budding in Hydra: In Hydra, a small protuberance arises from one side of the body. The protuberance grows and develops adult like structure. It develops hypostome and tentacles at its free end and also develops a basal disc at the point of attachment with the parent organism and finally gets detached to lead an independent life. The given diagram illustrates budding in Hydra: (ii) Vegetative propagation is an asexual method of reproduction in plants. In this method, new plants are obtained from the parts of old plants (like stems, roots and leaves), without the help of any reproductive organs. Advantages of vegetative propagation are as follows: (1) Vegetative propagation is usually used for the propagation of those plants which produce either very few seeds or do not produce viable seeds. (2) Seedless plants can be obtained by artificial vegetative propagation."
    },
    {
        "question": "44. The modes by which various organisms reproduce depend on the body design of the organisms. In asexual reproduction, a single individual parent produces offsprings without the involvement of gametes. This method is a common means of increasing the offsprings rapidly under favourable conditions. Asexual reproduction occurs mostly in unicellular organisms, some plants and certain simple multicellular animals. (a) State the name of the organism in which binary fission takes place in a definite orientation. Also name the disease caused by this organism. (b) List any two advantages of producing plants through vegetative propagation. (c) Explain the process of budding in Hydra. OR (c) What happens when : (1) a Spirogyra filament matures and attains a considerable length, and (II) a sporangia in Rhizopus bursts on maturation? (Term II, 2021-22)",
        "answer": "44. OR (c) (1) When a mature Spirogyra filament attains considerable length it simply breaks into two or more fragments and each fragment, then grows into a new Spirogyra. (II) The sporangia of Rhizopus contain cells or spores that can eventually develop into new Rhizopus individuals when it bursts on maturation.."
    },
    {
        "question": "45. (a) Name the mode of reproduction of the following organisms and state the important feature of each mode : (i) Planaria (ii) Hydra (iii) Rhizopus (b) We can develop new plants from the leaves of Bryophyllum. Comment. (c) List two advantages of vegetative propagation over other modes of reproduction. (2020)",
        "answer": "45. (a) (i) Planaria - Regeneration - Regeneration of organism from its cut body parts occurs by the process of growth and development.  - Regeneration is an asexual mode of reproduction common in lower plants and animals. (ii) Hydra - Budding - In budding, a small part of the body of the parent organism grows out as a bud which on detaching forms a new organism. (iii) Rhizopus - Spores - Spores are usually produced in sporangia. - Spore formation is a common method of an asexual reproduction in bacteria and most of the fungi. (b) The leaves of a Bryophyllum have special type of buds in their margins. These buds may get detached from the leaves, fall to ground and then grow to produce new Bryophyllum plants. The buds can also drop to the ground together with the leaf and then grow to produce new plants. (c) Advantages of vegetative propagation are: (i) The new plants produced by artificial vegetative propagation are exactly like the parent plants. (ii) Many plants can be grown from one plant by vegetative propagation."
    },
    {
        "question": "46. (a) Although Amoeba and Leishmania, both show same mode of reproduction, but the process of reproduction is carried out in different ways. Identify their mode of reproduction and mention the way it is carried out in the two species. (b) What is regeneration? Explain with the help of a diagram how this process is carried out in Planaria. (c) Name the part of Rhizopus in which spores are formed. State the condition under which spores grow into a new individual. (2019 C)",
        "answer": "46. (a) Amoeba and Leishmania both shows binary fission. Binary fission involves division of cell into nearly equal sized identical daughter cells.  - In Amoeba, simple binary fission or irregular binary fission occurs in which division occur through any plane. - In Leishmania, longitudinal binary fission the plane of division passes along the longitudinal axis of the animal. (b) Refer to answer"
    }
]